<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Men among the Blocks</title>
    <link>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Men among the Blocks</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 21:30:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bitcoin in Practice (Part II)</title>
      <link>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/bitcoin-in-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 21:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/bitcoin-in-practice/</guid>
      <description>‹ Back to Part I
Technical considerations Bitcoin is called a cryptocurrency because the network on which it runs relies on public key cryptography, a technique that allows people and systems to communicate securely over a public, insecure channel such as the Internet. In the future I will come up with a more thorough explanation of public key cryptography, and what its possibilities and limitations are, but for now a simplified model of how Bitcoin works is probably enough to understand its basic operations (Edit: You can read Part I of my intro to public key cryptography here).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bitcoin as Idea (Part I)</title>
      <link>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/bitcoin-as-idea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:00:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/bitcoin-as-idea/</guid>
      <description>To Part II ›
Crypto in general, and Bitcoin in particular used to be quite the hot topic in the tech community back in around 2016-2017, at least from what I could gauge at the time in online circles and in and around the tech hubs of Bucharest. However, I remember at the time having the distinct impression that such enthusiasm was mostly restricted to Bitcoin as a novel financial instrument, a perspective sometimes crossing into treating it as a kind of for-real, totally-legit get-rich-quick (trust the tech, bro!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Martian Chronicles - Ray Bradbury</title>
      <link>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/the-martian-chronicles-ray-bradbury/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 22:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/the-martian-chronicles-ray-bradbury/</guid>
      <description>The night came down around them, and there were stars. But Timothy couldn&amp;rsquo;t find Earth. It had already set.
&amp;ndash; The Martian Chronicles, p. 240 Ray Bradbury&amp;rsquo;s The Martian Chronicles is a melancholy book, in a way reminiscent of the great tradition of the Western. It is a tale of dusty, empty plains, haunted by deep time and the ghosts of the past, slowly becoming the birthplace of a new world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conspiracy theories and dogmatic thinking</title>
      <link>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/dogma-conspiracies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.amongtheblocks.com/posts/dogma-conspiracies/</guid>
      <description>Perhaps it is tempting to sneer at anti intellectual conspiracy peddling as fundamentally stupid but it does present a genuinely interesting epistemological problem in addition to the practical ones of how to approach someone who literally lives in a different world from you.
Maybe the attraction to dogmatic thinking is a measure of tiredness with postmodernity, in which micro-&amp;ldquo;grand narratives&amp;rdquo; are constantly shifted, morphed, spliced then discarded (think of stuff like self-help, motivational speakers or &amp;ldquo;financial education&amp;rdquo; on the socially-accepted end, Western Buddhism, New Age and Richard Dawkins-esque cultish Atheism somewhere in the middle, and conspiracy theories and the like on the extreme end).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
